<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>Crypto and Code</title>
    <link href="https://gisli.hamstur.is/atom.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://gisli.hamstur.is" />
    <id>https://gisli.hamstur.is/atom.xml</id>
    <author>
        <name>Gísli Kristjánsson</name>
        <email>gislik@hamstur.is</email>
    </author>
    <updated>2020-08-29T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <entry>
    <title><![CDATA[2020-08-29-understanding-ethereum-by-studying-the-source-code]]></title>
    <link href="https://gisli.hamstur.is/2020/08/understanding-ethereum-by-studying-the-source-code/index.html" />
    <id>https://gisli.hamstur.is/2020/08/understanding-ethereum-by-studying-the-source-code/index.html</id>
    <published>2020-08-29T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2020-08-29T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[For deep understanding it helps to get your hands dirty. Armed with the whitepaper, the yellow paper and the source code for the Go implementation we dive into the inner workings of Ethereum. In this Saturday long read, we cover among other things the state model, the peer-to-peer network, the EVM and the consensus algorithm. Lastly we discuss the Ethereum ice-age and why it exists. So prepare yourself a nice cup of coffee ☕️ and jump in!]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title><![CDATA[2020-08-24-a-bref-history-of-ethereum]]></title>
    <link href="https://gisli.hamstur.is/2020/08/a-bref-history-of-ethereum/index.html" />
    <id>https://gisli.hamstur.is/2020/08/a-bref-history-of-ethereum/index.html</id>
    <published>2020-08-24T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2020-08-24T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Ethereum, the second largest cryptocurrency by market cap, was proposed by Vitalik Buterin in 2013. Its intended purpose was to provide a blockchain with a Turing-complete programming language allowing users to extend its functionality by uploading custom code. The code could be used to create digital assets to represent custom currencies and financial instruments, the ownership of an underlying physical device, non-fungible assets such as domain names, as well as more complex applications involving having digital assets being directly controlled by a piece of code implementing arbitrary rules  or even blockchain-based decentralized autonomous organizations.]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title><![CDATA[2020-08-20-my-personal-hakyll-cheatsheet]]></title>
    <link href="https://gisli.hamstur.is/2020/08/my-personal-hakyll-cheatsheet/index.html" />
    <id>https://gisli.hamstur.is/2020/08/my-personal-hakyll-cheatsheet/index.html</id>
    <published>2020-08-20T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2020-08-20T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[A cheatsheet for my future self. We cover using the Hakyll eDSL to write website rules, advanced configuration which enables interesting features such as auto-generation of table of contents and \( \LaTeX \) math support on this website as well as discussion on how to roll your own Hakyll constructs.]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title><![CDATA[2014-10-02-receiving-bitcoins]]></title>
    <link href="https://gisli.hamstur.is/2014/10/receiving-bitcoins/index.html" />
    <id>https://gisli.hamstur.is/2014/10/receiving-bitcoins/index.html</id>
    <published>2014-10-02T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2014-10-02T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[The goal is to use Haskell to receive satoshis in as simple manner as possible by  generate a private key and deriveing from it an address. Using the address we can receive the coins and as long as we keep the key safe we can spend it later using any wallet which supports importing WIF keys.]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title><![CDATA[2014-08-20-bootstrapping-haskell-for-bitcoin-development]]></title>
    <link href="https://gisli.hamstur.is/2014/08/bootstrapping-haskell-for-bitcoin-development/index.html" />
    <id>https://gisli.hamstur.is/2014/08/bootstrapping-haskell-for-bitcoin-development/index.html</id>
    <published>2014-08-20T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2014-08-20T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It’s time to get our hands dirty. Let’s begin bootstrapping our Haskell development environment. Before we proceed it’s probably fair to note that it’s <em>very</em> early days for Bitcoin development using Haskell and like users of most languages one should expect the Bitcoin libraries to be changing rapidly.]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title><![CDATA[2014-08-13-bitcoin-wallets]]></title>
    <link href="https://gisli.hamstur.is/2014/08/bitcoin-wallets/index.html" />
    <id>https://gisli.hamstur.is/2014/08/bitcoin-wallets/index.html</id>
    <published>2014-08-13T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2014-08-13T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In this blog post I’m going to concentrate on <a href="https://bitcoin.org/en/choose-your-wallet">Bitcoin wallets</a> which will be our foundation for a more developer-oriented discussion. Wallets are analogous to web browsers in that they are the main interface for end users to interact with the network. In its simplest form it is a file which contains a collection of <a href="https://en.bitcoin.it/wiki/Private_key">private keys</a>. In addition the wallet software usually takes care of communicating with peers, managing the blockchain and keeping records of wallet transactions.]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title><![CDATA[2014-08-03-bitcoin-from-a-developers-perspective]]></title>
    <link href="https://gisli.hamstur.is/2014/08/bitcoin-from-a-developers-perspective/index.html" />
    <id>https://gisli.hamstur.is/2014/08/bitcoin-from-a-developers-perspective/index.html</id>
    <published>2014-08-03T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2014-08-03T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://bitcoin.org/en/">Bitcoin</a> is an exciting new technology invented by the mysterious <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Satoshi_Nakamoto">Satoshi</a> in 2009 which has been gaining some serious traction in the last few months. Although there are many introductory blog posts about Bitcoin there aren’t necessarily many which tackle the subject from a developer’s perspective.]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title><![CDATA[2012-12-14-network-programming-in-haskell]]></title>
    <link href="https://gisli.hamstur.is/2012/12/network-programming-in-haskell/index.html" />
    <id>https://gisli.hamstur.is/2012/12/network-programming-in-haskell/index.html</id>
    <published>2012-12-14T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2012-12-14T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>At work we use <a href="http://clojure.org">Clojure</a> as our primary implementation language. I wrote a <a href="http://appvise.me/2011/03/why-we-are-choosing-clojure-as-our-main-programming-language/">blog post</a> about the decision which got a lot of attention from the <a href="http://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=2350381">Hacker News</a> community. While we are extremely happy with our decision we have started to deploy some <a href="http://www.haskell.org/">Haskell</a> code on some low memory VPS we deploy.</p>
<p>Some of the machines we deploy are 256M and 512M instances and with multiple instances of the JVM the machines start swapping to disk sooner or later. The other day we needed a simple way to forward all HTTP traffic received by our DNS servers to our website. It seemed like the perfect project to introduce Haskell since the code is independent of everything else and extremely simple; just output a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_HTTP_status_codes#3xx_Redirection">HTTP 301 redirect</a> response no matter what was received on the socket.</p>
<p>The resulting code is as close to a networking skeleton written in Haskell which I hope others will benefit from when starting a Haskell project involving network communication. ]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title><![CDATA[2010-02-18-optical-mouse-scanner-location-awareness]]></title>
    <link href="https://gisli.hamstur.is/2010/02/optical-mouse-scanner-location-awareness/index.html" />
    <id>https://gisli.hamstur.is/2010/02/optical-mouse-scanner-location-awareness/index.html</id>
    <published>2010-02-18T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2010-02-18T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of the problems in the world of moving robots is the task of figuring out where robot is. One way is to mount a GPS-module on the robot. Simpler solutions might include methods that measure how many rounds the wheels have spun and (with the help of the diameter of the wheels and our friend π) calculate the distance travelled. What if the wheel spins or slides? Then the robot “thinks” it’s further along than it actually is.]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title><![CDATA[2009-12-12-line-following-robot]]></title>
    <link href="https://gisli.hamstur.is/2009/12/line-following-robot/index.html" />
    <id>https://gisli.hamstur.is/2009/12/line-following-robot/index.html</id>
    <published>2009-12-12T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2009-12-12T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[On our mission to learn Robotics an opportunity presented it self; a line-following competition hosted by IEEE Iceland, November 22nd, 2009. On the teams arrival it was announced that the track was a modeled after the F1 Suzuka track in Japan. We had designed a super slick car racer and implemented a PID controller using an Arduino board. The race was on!]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title><![CDATA[2009-10-13-from-happs-to-happstack]]></title>
    <link href="https://gisli.hamstur.is/2009/10/from-happs-to-happstack/index.html" />
    <id>https://gisli.hamstur.is/2009/10/from-happs-to-happstack/index.html</id>
    <published>2009-10-13T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2009-10-13T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>
I have been dreading porting my Blog application from <em>HAppS</em> to <a href="happstack.com"><em>Happstack</em></a> for a long time now. It is however apparent that <em>HAppS</em> is dying and <em>Happstack</em> (a fork of <em>HAppS</em> designed to take things further) was the only way to roll.
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title><![CDATA[2009-09-28-rise-of-the-mechatron]]></title>
    <link href="https://gisli.hamstur.is/2009/09/rise-of-the-mechatron/index.html" />
    <id>https://gisli.hamstur.is/2009/09/rise-of-the-mechatron/index.html</id>
    <published>2009-09-28T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2009-09-28T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Mechatronics is an interest that my colleague Andri and I share. For some months we have been trying to initiate a Mechatronics project but for some reason we never seem to be able to start even though we’re both pretty motivated.]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title><![CDATA[2009-05-05-model-migration]]></title>
    <link href="https://gisli.hamstur.is/2009/05/model-migration/index.html" />
    <id>https://gisli.hamstur.is/2009/05/model-migration/index.html</id>
    <published>2009-05-05T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2009-05-05T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>
My <a href="http://baldurkristjans.is">brother</a> has been asking me for a new feature for some time now. It’s a simple video feature where instead of showing a picture when clicked on a video begins to play. I had been holding this project off for a while because I knew that model migration would probably be a hazzle.
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title><![CDATA[2009-01-20-baldurkristjans.is-screen-cast-code-and-more]]></title>
    <link href="https://gisli.hamstur.is/2009/01/baldurkristjans.is-screen-cast-code-and-more/index.html" />
    <id>https://gisli.hamstur.is/2009/01/baldurkristjans.is-screen-cast-code-and-more/index.html</id>
    <published>2009-01-20T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2009-01-20T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>
As mentioned in my <a href="http://twitter.com/gislik/statuses/1121717423">tweet</a> my brother’s online <a href="http://baldurkristjans.is">photo album</a> went live last Thursday. Since then I’ve been trying to think not so much about it because this project had started to consume my brain leaving little space for anything else (including <a href="http://conqueringsleepapnea.com/images/insomnia_2.jpg">sleeping</a>). I’m happy with the responses he’s been getting over the last couple of days - and the most important thing; he’s happy.
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title><![CDATA[2009-01-05-Ive-been-busy-over-christmas]]></title>
    <link href="https://gisli.hamstur.is/2009/01/Ive-been-busy-over-christmas/index.html" />
    <id>https://gisli.hamstur.is/2009/01/Ive-been-busy-over-christmas/index.html</id>
    <published>2009-01-05T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2009-01-05T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>
… but there’s no activity on your blog you may say. Well I decided to do my <a href="http://baldurkristjans.is/">brother</a> a favor. He is a professional photographer working for a photo gallery called <a href="http://magg.is/">Magg</a> but with his own <em>clientele</em>. Now facing changes in the photographic scene as the recession begins to creep in he wanted to strengthen his own professional presence. The vehicle for such a requirement was an online photo gallery (due to open this week) with some of his more artistic images.
]]></summary>
</entry>

</feed>
